<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A guide to repentance. Or, The character and behaviour of the devout Christian in retirement Psal. 119. 54, 60. I called my own ways to remembrance, ... commandments. By John Inett, M.A. chanter and residentiary of the cathedral church of Lincoln.</title>
            <author>Inett, John, 1647-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I157A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1851:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A guide to repentance. Or, The character and behaviour of the devout Christian in retirement Psal. 119. 54, 60. I called my own ways to remembrance, ... commandments. By John Inett, M.A. chanter and residentiary of the cathedral church of Lincoln.</title>
                  <author>Inett, John, 1647-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 96 p. : ill. (frontis.)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for M. Wotton, at the Three Daggers in Fleetstreet, and T. Walker in Lincoln,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Frontis. = an engraving of a woman kneeling in devotion with imprint of M. Wotton, at the Three Daggers.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GUIDE TO Repentance. OR, The Character and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of the Devout Chriſtian in Retirement.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 119. 54, 60.</bibl>
               <p>I called my own ways to remembrance, and turned my Feet unto thy Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: I made haſte and delayed not to keep thy Commandments.</p>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>John Inett,</hi> M. A. Chanter and Reſidentiary of the Cathedral Church of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>M. Wotton,</hi> at the <hi>Three Daggers</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> and <hi>T. Walker</hi> in <hi>Lincoln,</hi> 1692.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>London Printed for M. Wotton at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 3 Daggers in Fleet Street.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Sir <hi>Richard Newdigate,</hi> Bar.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough I know you have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted your ſelf not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with all the Gentile and Politer Parts of Learning that ſerve either for Uſe of Accompliſhments to thoſe you your Quality, but are a very good Judge of Books of this kind; yet I am ſo well aſſured that you can be candid as well as juſt; and value Books by the Spirit and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and Poſſibilities of their being uſeful, rather than the art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Meaſures and Addreſs with which they are written; That with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ceremony or Apology, I preſume
<pb facs="tcp:32171:5"/>to preſent you with, and prefix your Name to one that has nothing but the Charity of its Intention to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie its being made Publick. The frequent Returns of the late pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Fasts, ſeeming to have made ſome Impreſſions on the Minds of People; and the ſeriouſneſs that on thoſe Occaſions appeared in their Faces, giving ſome Grounds to hope that an Addreſs of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, might be uſeful: This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration prevailed over all the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions that commonly lie in the way of ſuch Attempts, and the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Deſign ſo over-ballanc'd the viſible Imperfections with which it was managed, that without giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Thoughts time to cool, theſe Papers were put out of my hands
<pb facs="tcp:32171:5"/>with the haste and careleſsneſs with which they were written. But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuffered my Hopes and Wiſhes to ſurprize, rather than regularly gain a Conſent to their becoming Publick; my Judgment, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated againſt the Book with ſo full a Conſent, followed my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations in the Epiſtle; and the Uneaſineſs that accompanied the one, with ſo ſtrong and irreſiſtable a Biaſs, led me to the other, that I could not deny my ſelf ſo ſenſible a Pleaſure, as the publick acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of the many Obligations you have laid upon me; for that generous Paſſion with which (I can by experience, ſay) you ſerve your Friends; as it redoubles the Obligations you lay upon them, ſo it
<pb facs="tcp:32171:6"/>derives ſuch a Value and Merit upon your Friendſhip and Favours, that it ſhall be ever my Ambition to Publiſh my ſelf, and be Esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged Friend, and moſt Humble Servant, <hi>JOHN INETT.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:6"/>
            <head>TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>BEſides the great Day of Expiation and Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of God's own appointment, and the many other Seaſons by the Authority he entruſted with his Church, conſecrated to a general Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and Devotion, the Prophets and Evangeliſts have given us manifeſt evidence of a voluntary Practice amongſt all the Devout People under
<pb facs="tcp:32171:7"/>the Law, in ſetting apart cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain portions of their Times for the great Purpoſes of Religion; which being accompanied with Abſtinence, are from thence called by the Name of <hi>Private Faſts;</hi> and ſo far did this Cuſtom prevail in the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Church,</hi> that the practice of the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> in faſting twice a Week, ſeems to have been a Copy from the retirement for Devotion and Repentance, practis'd by their better Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. The Buſineſs of the <hi>Phariſee</hi> was Oſtentation and Vanity; yet our Saviour, who obſerved, and ſet a Mark up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Hypocriſie, not only allowed and juſtified their
<pb facs="tcp:32171:7"/>practice, but excuſed the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of his Diſciples, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable to their preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; but at the ſame time declared, that when the Bridegroom was taken away, they ſhould faſt in thoſe days: In which Diſcourſe, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our has ſet the Thing in its true light; aſſerting Faſting a Means and Help to, not an Act of Piety; and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Merit and Neceſſity, has allowed the Uſefulneſs, and aſſerted the Benefit; and in his excellent Sermon on the Mount, he not only gave Rules for the conduct of it, but by his own exemplary Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, and frequent Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:32171:8"/>for Devotion, poſſeſſed his Followers with ſo high an opinion of the great Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Retirement for Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Devotion, that it became a general Practice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the devouter Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of the firſt Ages. A Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice ſo far approved by all their penitential Canons, that it was always one Ingredient in the recovery and reſtoring of Offenders to the Favour of God, and the Communion of his Church, and had ſo great a ſhare in the primitive Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, that Eccleſiaſtical Story ſcarce affords an Inſtance of a Penitent reſtored without it. But when Perſecution, and the
<pb facs="tcp:32171:8"/>Inhumanity of their Enemies had forced ſome great Men into Deſarts, they endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by great Auſterities and Devotions to conſecrate their Fate, and excuſe the withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Light from Men, by rendering it more bright and illuſtrious before God, and by a more eminent ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their converſe with him, in ſome meaſure atone for the omiſſion of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities and good Offices they owed to Mankind. Theſe Examples meeting with the unhappy Circumſtances the Chriſtian-Church ſtrugled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the firſt Ages, drew ſuch numbers of Chriſtians into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement
<pb facs="tcp:32171:9"/>as peopled the Rocks and Deſarts, and made it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to reduce them to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety and rules of living; where Induſtry and Devotion made up their Character, and a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Labour, and Prayers, and Holy Hymns, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations took up their time.</p>
            <p>Thus far ſolitude and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement were innocent, and gained ſo much reputation in the Chriſtian World, as made it eaſie to ſome deſigning Men in the ſucceeding Ages, to ſerve themſelves on the eſteem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement had obtained. This Deſign falling in with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was conducted with ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:32171:9"/>art, that in time the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs got ground of the World, and a ſhew of renouncing it drew after it ſuch a train of Wealth and Greatneſs, that the pretence of Poverty and Humilty ſerved all the ends of Convetouſneſs and Ambition, and the Vows of Chaſtity and Obedience miniſtred to all the purpoſes of Folly; and the Fleſh and the World were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved under the colour of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying and renouncing them. The holy purpoſes and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of thoſe Holy Men, who had done Honour to retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, were reſolved into an uncouth habit, their induſtry to caſe and ſloth, their auſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:32171:10"/>to wearing a Diſcipline, a Scapulary, or a Cord, and their devout and ardent Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to a telling over a number of dry <hi>Ave Maria</hi>'s, by the help of the <hi>Roſary,</hi> which is ſo dull and inſipid a kind of Devotion, that if either the Senſe or Piety could be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; yet it has ſo little of the Primitive Spirit, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ion of St. <hi>Dominick</hi> would doubtleſs have met with other entertainment than his admirers have beſtow'd upon it, had he hapned to live ſome Ages ſooner. But whilſt the ancient Piety and Devotion thus degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the Pretenſions thereunto, grew afreſh out of their aſhes,
<pb facs="tcp:32171:10"/>and Merit and Perfection were with great confidence challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſeveral Orders of Recluſes, and renouncing the World, though the leaſt thing in their Character; under theſe Pretenſions being uſeleſs, grew up into ſuch Credit, that the Commands and Tears of a Father were not ſtrong enough to with-hold an only. Child from a Cloiſter, nor the conjugal Ties and Vows of Fidelity, a diſcontented Wife. But the Pretence of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Phariſees</hi> was revived with ſuch advantages, that the Name of <hi>Corban,</hi> did not only excuſe his Wealth, but the Poſſeſſor too; and ſet him
<pb facs="tcp:32171:11"/>at Liberty, not only to leave a Father, or a Mother, a Child, or a Family, to the Mercy of the World; but voided the Right of his Brother, his Prince, his Country, his Wife, or his Child, to his Charity, his Counſel, his Service, or his Care, and not only broke through, but cancelled the moſt ſacred Ties both of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Religion. Theſe were ſuch Abuſes of Retirement, that it is not to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered if the Contempt and Indignation they deſerved, leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen'd the eſteem of every thing that had ſerv'd to colour them, and drew a Suſpicion on the Diſcipline, that in the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:32171:11"/>ages of Religion had mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to all the End of Piety and Devotion; and this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice falling in with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of Sloth, and Luxury, and Indevotion, had too much influence on ſome that embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Reformation; but did not ſo far prevail in this Church, but that beſides the ſtated <hi>Faſts</hi> and <hi>Vigils,</hi> Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Piety and Devotion, had a juſt regard in theſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, amongſt the People of Thought and Leiſure, till our <hi>unhappy Wars</hi> let in a Torrent of Impiety upon us, and the ill-grounded Fears of a relapſe to the Superſtition of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> run ſome Men
<pb facs="tcp:32171:12"/>into Superſtition of another kind; for he that places <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> and <hi>Merit</hi> in laying aſide the proper Means and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Piety and Devotion, and he who places Holineſs in the Uſe, are both alike guilty of Superſtition; and the Looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and Prophaneneſs which have purſued the former, have given us a ſenſible Evidence of the Miſchiefs that unhappy Miſtake has drawn down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us.</p>
            <p>In theſe unhappy Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, whilſt the Miſtakes of ſome have caſt a Blemiſh and Contempt on the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Methods of Holineſs and Devotion, and the Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb facs="tcp:32171:12"/>of others, has broke all the Reſtraints of Modeſty and good Manners, to reproach and deſpiſe them; it may look like the attempt of one unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the World, to offer at an Eſſay to recommend them to a due Conſideration and Regard. But when the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> complained of a general Apoſtacy and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Manners, and thought his Country gone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Falſe Gods,</hi> God checked the Immodeſty and want of Charity in the Prophet, and told him, that in the midſt of that Diſſolution, which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Epidemical, he had ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved himſelf <hi>ſeven Thouſand
<pb facs="tcp:32171:13"/>that had never bowed the knee to Baal;</hi> it would then be very unreaſonable, as well as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, to imagine, that in ſo great and flouriſhing a Church as that of <hi>England,</hi> God had not preſerved infinite Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, that with all Sincerity aſpire to the Primitive Piety and Devotion: For though the pomp and ſhews of auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, do not make that Figure with us, that poſſibly they may do in the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> though wrong Notions, and the too general Looſneſs have withdrawn ſome, and the bold Inſults of Prophaneneſs inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midated others, and thus leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened the Piety, and Vertue,
<pb facs="tcp:32171:13"/>and Decency, and Gravity of that Devotion, that bleſſed the firſt Age of the Reformation; yet without Vanity and Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, it may be ſaid, that there appears more plain, natural, and unaffected Piety in the Communion of this Church, than are commonly to be found amongſt other ſorts of Chriſtians. Which it may be no one thing (within the Compaſs of our own endeavours) would more improve, than a due ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of that her <hi>Rubrick,</hi> wherein ſhe directs her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to a Weekly Faſt; by which, I ſhall preſume to think, ſhe intends not ſo much a total abſtinence, or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="tcp:32171:14"/>kind of Diet, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe Periods for a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Review of our Lives, and more eſpecial Oblation of our Thanks and Prayers to God, accompanied with the ſtricteſt meaſures of Temperance: For though abſtinence be of admirable Uſe to ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, and not only redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the Piety of the Chriſtian in laying the Foundation of it in the Sacrifice of his appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite; but in kindling holy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, that give new Life and Vigour to his Devotions; yet there are other Tempers that not only fruſtrate, but pervert all the Religious Ends of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence: But he that has a
<pb facs="tcp:32171:14"/>Will to it, can want neither Ability, nor Time, to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate an Hour in a Week to Repentance and Devotion; he that cannot obſerve the <hi>Rubrick</hi> in a Day of Faſting, may confeſs his Sin to God, and beg his Pardon, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo oppreſs'd with Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but his buſie Thoughts may reflect on the Mercies he owes to God, or on his own Demerit. And if we conſider the general practice of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, it will appear an unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable and ſtupendious fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the affair which only deſerves our time and thought, ſhould only be neglected; or at the beſt, be only left to
<pb facs="tcp:32171:15"/>Chance and Accidents, whilſt every Trifle preſcribes to a certain portion of our Time and Care.</p>
            <p>But if Men would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded to do the ſame Juſtice to their greateſt Intereſt, that of the other World, which they do to thoſe of this, that is, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low themſelves Time to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, I doubt not but it would go a great way, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Cure of that Looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which has ſo fatally broke in upon us; but in reſtoring that Temperance and Charity; that Goodneſs and Beneficence, and that exemplary Holineſs and Vertue which the Religion of our Lord requires from us:
<pb facs="tcp:32171:15"/>To which bleſſed Ends, if the following Papers will any way contribute, either by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening the careleſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking, or encouraging or aſſiſting the better diſpoſed Chriſtian, they will anſwer, and reward the Intention with which they were written.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:16"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A <hi>Guide</hi> to the <hi>Devout Chriſtian:</hi> in Three Parts. The Firſt, containing Meditations and Prayers, affixed to the Days of the Week; together with many Occaſional Prayers for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Perſons. The Second, for more Perſons than one, or a whole Family, for every Day of the Week; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with many Occaſional Prayers. The Third, containing a Diſcourſe of the Nature and Neceſſity of the Holy Sacrament; together with Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereon, Prayers and Directions for the worthy Receiving thereof. To which is added, A Prayer for <hi>Aſh-Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday,</hi> or any other Time in <hi>Lent;</hi> for <hi>Good-Friday,</hi> and any Day of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faſting. <hi>The Second Edition Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</hi> Written by the ſame Author.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32171:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. The Reaſons which lead the Devout Chriſtian to retire. 2. His Notions of Retirement. 3. His Behaviour therein.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <p>1. THE Union of the Soul and Body, is a Secret the Devout Chriſtian does not pretend to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate; nor to explain the Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that attend it: But that the Body has a mighty influence on the Soul, and the Notices and Conceptions of the Underſtanding
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32171:17"/>have a tincture from the matter of which the Body is formed, is as manifeſt as the different Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which the Things of this and the other World make on the Minds of Men, by a ſimilitude of Nature, and the immediate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs they have to our Senſes: The former have a mighty influence, whilſt the latter, having no acceſs to the Soul but by the Miniſtry of the Body, are diſcoloured by the Medium through which they paſs, and are ſo leſſened in our eſtimation and regard, that every Trifle becomes a Rival; and our ſenſitive part ſo favours the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions of the World, that it is very apt to engroſs our time and our care. <hi>Iſrael</hi>-like, we fix ſo paſſionately on the Earthly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> that 'tis ſome pain to bring our ſelves to due reflections on the Joys which lie beyond it; and 'tis ſo difficult to entertain the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32171:17"/>thoughts of both together, that 'tis hard, if not impoſſible, for the beſt of Men to preſerve a juſt <hi>Idea</hi> of another Life, whilſt they give up themſelves to the hurry and the noiſe of This. Hence the Devout Chriſtian concludes it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſet a-part, certain Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his time, when laying aſide all thoughts of This, he may entertain himſelf with thoſe of the other World.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <p>2. He does not abandon the Station God has ſet him in; he does not fly to a Cloyſter or a Deſart, nor believe he ſhall be more ſerviceable to God by ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring himſelf uſeleſs to Men; that Walls will purge the Corruptions which lodge in his Nature, or Solitude quench the Fire he carries thither in his Blood. Though he has a reverence for thoſe Holy Men, whom Perſecution or Choice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32171:18"/>led to a Solitude; yet he cannot believe that the Holy Solitaires of old ever intended, by their Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to unpeople the World; or that God ever intended we ſhould baniſh our ſelves from Society, to which he planted a tendency in our very Natures; or that he who made us to be helpful to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, will put a value on a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Affront and Contradiction to the Law of our Natures; or that the higheſt Inſtitution of Charity, (the Goſpel,) will ever allow the beſt pretenſions to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat it, and render Men unuſeful to the World.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <p>3. Yet he believes it of great moment to make frequent retreats from the World, to abandon and lay aſide the purſuit and thoughts thereof, to entertain himſelf with the conſiderations of and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to a better State; and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32171:18"/>this he looks upon as neceſſary as Temperance and Phyſick to his Body, or Accounts to his Eſtate. If the Health of his Body will permit, Abſtinence accompanies him to his Cloſet, and his Body feels the reſentment his Sin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves; at leaſt he Faſts to his Father that ſees in ſecret; he does not ſerve his Vanity on his retreat; it does not make him ſowre, uneaſie, or out of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour; nor does he think his Converſation ought to carry the marks of thoſe ſad reflections that poſſeſſed his Soul; 'tis enough to him that God is the Witneſs to his ſorrow and reſentment; that he has poured out his Soul before him; that he who can reward him openly, can hear the gentleſt ſigh, or the ſofteſt Prayer; and thus aſſured, a profound Humility, and an awful ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence accompany him in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32171:19"/>to his Cloſet, where his Repentance and his Prayers have their due place; he knows that he who fills the Heavens, will dwell with the humble and contrite Heart; and the high and lofty one, who inhabits Eternity, will hear and not deſpiſe the Prayer of the deſtitute; that he whoſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is over all his Works, whoſe Grace is ſufficient for the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Offender, will grant Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto Life to thoſe that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely ſeek for it: And in this aſſurance his firſt Addreſs is to God, that he who is the Creator and Lover of Souls, who thought fit to make Men after his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and redeem them with the ineſtimable Merits of his Son, and in his Name has Preached repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to all the World, and to whom nothing is impoſſible, would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able him to make a right judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his own ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32171:19"/>and grant him repentance unto Life Eternal; and that this may not end in ineffectual wiſhes, his firſt care is to inform himſelf of the Nature of that Duty God, and the intereſt of his own Soul, have made ſo neceſſary.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:32171:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1. The Penitents opinion of the poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and neceſſity of Repentance, and the danger of deferring it. 2. His ſorrow for ſin. 3. His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to forſake it. 4. His beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour when ſurprized to the ſin he reſolved againſt. 5. His thoughts of the ſecond part of Repentance, the meaſures by which he diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes it from the ineffectual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and judges of his ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the practice thereof. 6. Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt his relapſe, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the duty of Repentance. 7. Practice of it, how managed. 8. When removed.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <p>1. THe natural notices of God's Goodneſs and Mercy, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it ſo reaſonable to believe, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32171:20"/>he has made that plain, and intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, and practicable, which he has made neceſſary; that when he finds Repentance charged upon the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and enforced with the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Death eternal, the devout Chriſtian concludes it a duty in the reach of every capacity, and by the Grace of God within the power of the ſinner; and does neither diſturb himſelf with nice and elaborate ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations and enquiries about it, nor with dangerous conceits of its being impracticable; but relying on that All-wiſe Goodneſs that deſigned it a Remedy and a Bleſſing to fallen Mankind, he conducts his ſearch by thoſe diſcoveries that God has given, and his hopes by the Grace and Aids he has promiſed; aſſures himſelf the Repentance God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes in his Word, is that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; and the Merits of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Jeſus, which in favour of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have changed he Primitive me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32171:21"/>of Salvation. And advanced ſorrow, and remorſe, and a hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty endeavour of pleaſing God, into the room of integrity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinning obedience, will not only give a value to the duty being done, but procure ability to perform it. Having thus laid the foundations of his Faith and Hopes in the Goodneſs of God, and the Merits of his Son, he addreſſes himſelf to the Treaſury of Holy Truths God intended for his Guide, where Repentance is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed ſometimes by the perturbation which is raiſed in the ſoul of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, by a reflection on his ſin, or the frightful apprehenſions that a ſenſe of ſin produces in us. Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls it <hi>a godly ſorrow,</hi> and faith, <hi>That a godly ſorrow works Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance to Salvation.</hi> Sometimes it is deſcribed by the effect which the ſenſe of ſin and the hopes of pardon produce in the Heart and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or in the Lives and Manners
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32171:21"/>of Men. Thus in the common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Prophets, Repentance is <hi>making a clean and a new ſpirit, turning from our evil ways; or doing that which is lawful and right,</hi> and <hi>turning unto God.</hi> From which va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of expreſſions, he concludes Repentance to be ſuch a ſenſe and apprehenſion of the guilt and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſin, as begets a hearty ſorrow for it, and a real diſlike and hatred of all ſin, together with a ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and honeſt endeavour to forſake it, to do better, and live in obedience to the Laws of God. And as this appears to be the method of reconciling ſinners unto God, the method himſelf has appointed, and the ſatisfactions of our Lord have purchaſed and given a value and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy to: ſo the devout Chriſtian bleſſes God for it, and though he do not preſume to limit the Mercy of God, or make himſelf a Judge of his brother, yet he believes he may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32171:22"/>and ought to judge himſelf; and concludes, that no Repentance can afford him a well-grounded hope of pardon, but that he lives to ſee the fruits of in the amendment of his life; and therefore his care is, to prevent the dangers of a late Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and ſatisfie himſelf of his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity by a timely and conſtant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of himſelf to the duty which God and the frailties of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature have made ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <p>2. The firſt part of his Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is ſuch a due ſenſe of the evil and danger of ſin, as begets a ſorrow for it, and an univerſal hatred and diſlike of it, manifeſted by a cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary and habitual forſaking the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice thereof. Though the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which fear makes on the minds of men, and the uneaſie reflections which are cauſed by danger, may be of great uſe in bringing men to a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32171:22"/>right judgment of their ſpiritual ſtate and condition; yet of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they come ſo far ſhort of true Repentance, that thoſe Schools which have allowed Attrition, or a forrow ariſing from fear of puniſhment, when accompanied with Abſolution, as effectual to all the ends of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, have not only laid a ſnare for Offenders, but aſſumed a power of changing the appointed methods of bringing ſinners to Salvation. But the guilt and turpitude, as well as danger of ſin, and a juſt regard to the Authority it violates, and the Goodneſs it offends, conduct the ſorrow of the Penitent; for he who is troubled becauſe God is offended, and his Honour abuſed, muſt on the ſame grounds regret every indignity offered to God. This conſideration inſpires the reſentment of the good Chriſtian, and he does not part with one ſin in exchange for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; he does not recal his love to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32171:23"/>an uneaſie, publick, or dangerous Vice, that all his paſſion may centre in the folly that lies in his boſom, that ſuits his complexion, and ſits eaſier and leſs viſible upon him. No; the Penitent has his meaſures of his love and hatred from above; every error, every failing, every miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, is the ſubject of his ſorrow; every folly calls forth his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but every wilful ſin covers his face with confuſion and ſhame. He is <hi>angry</hi> with himſelf, whenever he believes God is <hi>ſo;</hi> and by a juſtice on himſelf, labours to prevent that of God. His Couch, his Cloſet, or his Bed, do the buſineſs of the great Tribunal; there the ſin is laid open, there the ſinner is accuſed, arraigned, and condemned too; and juſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience gives him a proſpect of the miſeries that no tongue can tell.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:32171:23"/>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <p>3. But this is not all: The Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thinks it not enough that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge the quarrel of an offended God upon himſelf, that anguiſh and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs poſſeſs his Soul; but his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row grows up into a holy reſolution to forſake the ſin that had brought down the anger of God upon him; that for the poor and contemptible ſatisfactions of a ſenſe, put him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the hazard of an everlaſting ruine; he contemns its flatterings, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſes all its charms, and flies from it, as from the face of a Serpent. If he happen to be ſurprized, and inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency betray him to the ſin he hates, a new Deluge of Sorrow breaks in upon him, and all the confuſion and anguiſh that ſad reflections and guilty fears can produce, return up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Soul: yet he ſuffers not this to overwhelm him; he knows 'tis the reward of the other world to live free from all ſin; that the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32171:24"/>of that God that will not allow a habit of Vice, will yet have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the impotence of human Nature, and will make ſome abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the ſurpriſals no vigilance can prevent; and that he who has made us Men, and not Angels, will forgive the Sin he reſolved, and prayed, and ſtrove againſt, and does now lament; he comforts himſelf with the hopes that the habit, and not the ſingle act, ſhall denominate the Offender; that the unhappy Surprize he has faln under, ſhall not diſpoil him of the Reward or Character of the Penitent; and to juſtifie his Pretenſes and Hopes, ſets himſelf to the ſecond part of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; which is,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <p>5. In the Language of Holy Writ, deſcribed, by turning unto God, keeping his Statutes, and doing that which is Lawful and Right, keeping of his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32171:24"/>and making a clean Heart and a new Spirit; all which are Phraſes of the like importance, and ſignifie that the repentance, which God requires, is not a ſmall diſlike of Sin, ariſing from the regrets of an uneaſie Conſcience, but ſuch a change, as of a bad makes a good Man; ſuch as inſpires a juſt regard to the Honour of God, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the other World, and makes it the bent and deſire of the Soul to promote his Glory, by living in all obedience to his Laws, and by all poſſible expreſſions of Duty ſecure his Favour, and the Felicities of the Bleſſed State; and by his ſteddineſs in his purſuit of thoſe Bleſſed Ends, the Penitent makes his judgment of his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; he ſuſpects the ſorrow that ends in languid wiſhes, or leaves him at eaſe in the commiſſion of a known Sin; he doubts that Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that will permit a Man to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32171:25"/>fly into the Face of his Neighbours Sin, yet run with complacency in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Boſom of his own; that is ſevere on the Sins of the Publick, but eaſie to his own; that carries all his reſentment of Sin in his Face, and proclaims hoſtility in looks and words, whilſt there is Peace within, and his folly and his affections are at unity; he ſuſpects that repentance that is partial in executing the Divine Anger, or the performance of Holy Duties; that is cold and ſlow where his intereſt or conſtitution are on the ſide of Vice, but flies like lightning where his intereſt or natural aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions lead him to condemn a Sin; that ſpends all his Zeal on Trifles, and places his Hope in little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of vertue; that has fits and ſtarts; to Day all Fire, and to Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Water; whoſe Zeal is all flame for one hour, but cold and languſd the very next; but the Repentance
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32171:25"/>he contends for is ſteady and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the purſuit of all that is Good and Vertuous; that hates Vice in the faireſt dreſs, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt or the propenſions of Nature can ſet upon it; that loves Vertue under all the diſadvantages that 'tis capable of; that can part with a Luſt tender as the Eye, or dear as the Right Hand; and break through all the ſtruggles and regret of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Nature, to follow the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God; that with ſorrow beholds the crying Sins of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but with tears and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction looks upon the ſhare he has in the Publick Guilt. 'Tis not enough to the Penitent, that ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row covers his Face, unleſs it fill his Heart too; that he be angry with his Sin, but he parts with it too; he not only reflects with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion on what he has done amiſs, but flies where-ever his guilt leads him, whether to God or his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32171:26"/>for a Pardon; if God be the injured Perſon, his Tears and his Prayers carry his afflicted Soul to the Throne of Grace, and a broken and a contrite Heart recommend him to the compaſſions of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if his Brother be the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, reſtitution or ſatisfaction are the fruits and marks of his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; he begs pardon for little Offences, or with reſtitution is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to buy forgiveneſs, and believes that only to be the uſeful repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which calls him back from his Follies to his Duty, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily conducts him in it; that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes a holy awe and love of God, and a juſt care for his eternal welfare.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <p>6. But when Fleſh and Blood remonſtrate, and would draw him back from the ways of repentance, the penitent looks upon it, not only as a Duty, but as conſecrated
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32171:26"/>into a Bleſſing, and adores the Goodneſs that advanced it into the place of Innocence, and by ſo eaſie and gentle a remedy put it into his Power to recover the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity Sin had loſt, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage preponderates the trouble; and he is pleaſed to be healed, though the Phyſick be churliſh. If the Enemy, or his own Fears, magnifie the Difficulty or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Work too great, or of too little value, the Merits of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour come in to his aid; and he aſſures himſelf, that he who gave his Son to die to make him ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of living, will give his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to thoſe that ask it with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere intention to live.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <p>7. Thus the Penitent breaks through all the Difficulties that ſtand in his way, and from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate haſtens to experiment the pleaſures of being reconciled unto
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32171:27"/>God and in his own Converſion taſt the ſatisfactions which are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Joys above; he opens his Soul to God, calls his own and God's ways to remembrance, his Guilts and Follies; and the Mercies that have out-done them in number, have each their place in his Reflections; with a ſad and penſive Soul he beholds the one, and with aſtoniſhment the other; he is amazed at his Ingratitude and Madneſs, that could return the Goodneſs of ſo bountiful a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Contempt and Diſhonour; and ſerve his Luſt on that Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to which he owes his very being; but his amazement riſes higher, when he reflects on that unſpeakable Mercy that has ſpared him when he deſerved to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; that has poured new Bleſſings into his Boſom, when he deſerved nothing leſs; and purſued him with an unwearied Goodneſs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32171:27"/>and invincible Patience through all the Scenes of Sin and Folly; and amidſt all the Labirynths and Turnings, through which his Luſts had led him, been ſo conſtant in the repetition of his Favours, as if he had intended, by an inceſſant love, to force a Happineſs upon him, and with the importunities of a never-failing Goodneſs, not only lead, but compel him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: This he remembers with aſtoniſhment and joy; and that it may never be forgotten, he breaks through all the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of the World, to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part a Portion of his time, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double the favours of God, in freſh reflections upon them. 'Tis not enough to him, that the Sins and Mercies of the Day, have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Night a place in his thoughts; but he conſecrates a Portion of his time to lament the one, and adore the Goodneſs that beſtowed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32171:28"/>the other; not a Week paſſes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Solemn Hour conſecrated to Gratitude and Repentance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a freſh and deliberate account betwixt God and his Soul, where Sorrow and Joy, where Vows and Prayers and good Reſolutions, where Mortification and a Holy Revenge, have each their places, and by judging himſelf the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent prevents the terrours of a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal judgment, and by a wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge on himſelf diſarms the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power to puniſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <p>8. Nor do thoſe certain periods of Sorrow ſo limit the buſineſs of the Penitent, but his repentance is renewed afreſh when a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick calamity calls for it; the Fears, the Dangers, the Afflictions, or the crying Sins of a Nation, haſten him down into his own Soul; he is juſt and impartial in his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, whether he be not that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32171:28"/>
                     <hi>Achan,</hi> whoſe Sin drew down the Judgment, or the Danger that threatens; and believes it a Juſtice he owes to his Country, to lend his Tears and his Prayers to fill up the meaſures of a National Repentance; nay, though Wicked as <hi>Sodom,</hi> yet he believes it his Duty to make one amongſt thoſe whoſe righteouſneſs may help to ſave it; the ſtated, or the occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Faſts of the Church, have their due regard; he looks upon them as conſecrated to Devotion and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to Prayers and Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, and his Soul bears a part in the Solemnity; he is angry with himſelf when God is angry with a Nation, and believes his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure a fit ſubject for his own, and looks upon it as a Duty incumbent upon him to make one amongſt thoſe that Mourn in <hi>Sion,</hi> when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he is called by a juſt Authority, to lament his Anger, or implore his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32171:29"/>Bleſſings: But when all is peace and ſilent from without, the cares of that Immortal Being, God has committed to his truſt, are preſſing and importunate from within; the dangers that beſet him, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations that ſurround him, the burden of his Sins, and the Sins of his frailties, cry aloud for frequent retirements for the ends of Devotion and Repentance; and he believes the diſcharge of his Soul, into the Boſom of God, ſo neceſſary to leſſen the burden of his Guilt, and a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent account with himſelf of ſuch important moment to his laſt and great account with God, that he ſuffers not the importunity of the World to hinder his retirement; and that a Principle of Love and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and an humble ſenſe of his own demerit, may conduct his cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of himſelf and his addreſſes to God, he reflects on the Mercy and Compaſſions of God, and looks
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32171:29"/>back to his paſt courſe of life, recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting his ſins and follies; every greater tranſgreſſion is covered with a new ſorrow, and renews his ſuit for God's pardon and mercy; yet, that their guilt and number may not overwhelm his hope of mercy, nor his partiality teach him to forget the terms on which 'tis offered, he entertains himſelf with the thoughts of God's mercy, and the terms on which 'tis promiſed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:32171:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>1 Meditations on God's mercy to Penitents. 2. Prayer for God's aſſiſtance. 3. Confeſſion of ſins. 4. Penetential Litany. 5. A Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for Grace. 6. Faith. 7. Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 8. Preparation for Death and Judgment. 9. A Prayer of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation. 10. For the Church. 11. Kingdoms. 12. People. 13. Occaſional Prayers to be added.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>A Meditation on the Mercies of God, and his gracious promiſes to peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Sinners.</head>
                  <p>GOD created Man, that he might never want an eternal Subject of his mercy; that he might have a Being to which to impart his Goodneſs, and diſtinguiſh from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32171:30"/>the reſt of the Creation, by greater inſtances of that mercy which is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all his Works.</p>
                  <p>And when ſin had made a breach betwixt God and Man, and his Mercy might have given place to the ſeverer attribute of Juſtice, his Wiſdom and Power were ſet on work to reſtore ſinners to a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of that Mercy they had juſtly forfeited. He gave his Son, that they might not periſh; ſent him from Heaven, to preach Repentance and Remiſſion of their ſins, and was content he ſhould <hi>die,</hi> to capacitate them to <hi>live;</hi> and the Bleſſed Jeſus, that he might be the Image of his Father's Love and Goodneſs, as well as Glory, is come on purpoſe to be the Saviour of them that were loſt: and that he might be ſo, has conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted an Order of Men to beſeech ſinners in his ſtead to be reconciled unto God, and not only appointed them to be Guardians of his Truth,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32171:31"/>but Preachers of his Charity, who with an undiſtinguiſhing Goodneſs has tendred a pardon to all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to him by Repentance.</p>
                  <p>Has not God ſaid,<note place="margin">Ezek. 33.11.</note> 
                     <hi>That he would not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould turn from his ſin, and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi> and can I think that God can contradict himſelf, and believe 'tis his will I ſhould periſh, when he has ſaid, <hi>He would have me return and live?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Has he not ſaid,<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.18.</note> 
                     <hi>Though my ſin be as red as ſcarlet,</hi> yet if I ceaſe to do evil, and learn to do well, <hi>they ſhall be white as ſnow; though they be red as crimſon, they ſhall be as wool?</hi> and ſhall I doubt what God has affirmed?</p>
                  <p>Has he not ſaid,<note place="margin">John 3.16.</note> 
                     <hi>That he gave his Son, that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever believes in him, ſhould not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but have everlaſting life; That his death was intended as a ſacrifice
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32171:31"/>for all the world; or, That he taſted death for every man; That he would have all men come to the knowledge of his truth, that they might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi> and ſhall I diſtruſt that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that is thus frankly tendred to all the world?</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, I am a ſinner; but 'tis ſuch that need, and 'tis to ſuch that God has tendred mercy. I am a notorious offender; but 'tis for ſuch Chriſt has died. I am weary and heavy laden, and my iniquity is greater than I can bear; but 'tis to ſuch that Chriſt has promiſed reſt. And ſhall I rob my ſelf of that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy which alone can be ſufficient for me? ſhall I queſtion that Merit that is enough to ſave the World, or doubt the Goodneſs which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but my own impenitence can deprive me of? Oh no! thy Mercy, O bleſſed Father, ſhall be my refuge! Thy Merit, O bleſſed Jeſus, ſhall be the foundation of my hope; and let
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:32171:32"/>me never diſtruſt thy Goodneſs, O God my God!</p>
                  <p>Thus the Penitent having fixed in his ſoul a juſt Idea of that Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence God requires, and of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable Goodneſs and Merit that can give acceptance and value to it, haſtens to diſcharge his guilty fears into the boſom that can pity and forgive them.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:32171:32"/>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>2. His firſt, or Morning Prayer, acknowledging God's Mercy, and imploring his aſſiſtance and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt holy and eternal Father, by whoſe Care and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I have been preſerved the Night paſſed, and by whoſe Mercy and Favour I have a few hours to live, and fit my ſelf to die: To thy Name be eternal Thanks and Praiſe for theſe and all thy Mercies vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to me. The laſt Night my Soul might have been required at my hands, or in thy Juſtice thou mightſt have taken me in the very act of Sin to the Judgment-ſeat, and not have given me time to <hi>ſpeak,</hi> much leſs to <hi>repent;</hi> but thou haſt let me ſee, that thou canſt be good to me, though I have been evil; that thy patience and forbearance
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:32171:33"/>are greater than my provocations; and that thou canſt have pity on me, though I have had too little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on my own Soul. Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double thy Bleſſings upon me, by ſanctifying them to me, and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to make a wiſe and a good uſe of all the advantages of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and Advice, of time and opportunity, and all the means of Grace and Repentance thou vouch-ſafeſt unto me. Bleſs eſpecially my preſent endeavours to ſeek thy peace and favour, and teach me ſo to judge my ſelf, that I may not be condemned in the day of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:32171:33"/>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>3. A Confeſſion of Sins.</head>
                  <p>O Almighty God, who art a Searcher of the heart, and a Trier of the reins, and from whom no ſecrets are hid, and yet wouldſt have us confeſs our ſins unto thee, who art about our Path, about our Bed, and ſpieſt out all our ways: In mercy, O Lord, look down up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, who in the bitterneſs and anguiſh of my Soul come to proſtrate my ſelf before thee; my ſins are in thy ſight, and my unrighteouſneſs is not hid; the frailties of my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the corruptions of my Will, and the diſorders of my Life; my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of thy Mercies, my contempt of thy Judgments, my repeated vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of thy holy Laws, are more than I am able to expreſs: I have neither loved, nor ſerved, nor obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee as I ought to do; I have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:32171:34"/>broke through all the obligations of Duty and Intereſt, to purſue my Luſts and Follies; every little tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation has withdrawn me from thy Love and Service, whilſt thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous invitations, the mercy of thy promiſes and aſſiſtances of thy Grace and Spirit, have all been loſt upon me. O good God! I am troubled, I am aſhamed, and confounded! what ſhall I do, or whither ſhall I fly! how can I hope for thy Mercy, that have deſerved the rigours of thy Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice! But ſince it is thy will that I ſhould repent and live, look down, O Lord, in mercy upon me, who am unfit to look up unto thee, and let thy Grace form in me ſuch a ſenſe of my ſins, that I may hate and forſake them; and do thou, O Lord, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy multitude of Mercies, do away my offences. Lord, ſpare, forgive and pity me, for Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:32171:34"/>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>4. A Penitential <hi>Litany,</hi> or ſhort Prayers for <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Pardon</hi> and <hi>Grace.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>O God the Father, who wouldſt not the death of a ſinner, have mercy upon me.</p>
                  <p>O thou God of Mercy, that wouldſt have the ſinner repent and live, give me a due ſenſe of all my ſins, and then forgive and pity me.</p>
                  <p>O thou that wouldſt have all men come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth, and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, caſt me not away from thee.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:32171:35"/>
                  <p>O holy Father, who didſt ſo love the world, that thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt thy Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting Life; Have mercy upon me, a miſerable ſinner.</p>
                  <p>O thou that deſpiſeſt not a broken and a contrite heart, and whoſe Will and Power nothing can reſiſt: O do thou create a clean Heart, and renew a right Spirit within me. O ſay unto my ſoul, <hi>I will, be thou clean;</hi> and be it to thy ſervant according to thy word.</p>
                  <p>O thou that haſt no pleaſure in the death of him that dies, and haſt given thy Son to die, that ſinners may not die eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:32171:35"/>Spare me, Lord moſt holy, O God moſt mighty, and deliver me from the bitter pains of eternal Death.</p>
                  <p>O bleſſed Jeſus, who didſt die to give a worth and value to Repentance, and that Repentance and Remiſſion of ſins ſhould be preached to all the world in thy Name: O do thou make my Repentance ſuch as thou haſt required and wilt accept, and let thy Merits ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it effectual to the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſins.</p>
                  <p>O thou who didſt taſte death for every man, and laidſt down thy Life for thoſe who were dead in <hi>Adam,</hi> and haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to accept all ſuch as come
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:32171:36"/>unto thee: O caſt me not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from thee, but have mercy upon me, O God my God.</p>
                  <p>O thou that haſt bid ſuch as are weary and heavy laden <hi>come unto thee,</hi> and promiſed <hi>they ſhall find rest for their ſouls:</hi> O Lord, look down upon me, who in the bitterneſs and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of my ſoul come unto thee, and have mercy upon me.</p>
                  <p>O Holy and Ever-bleſſed Spirit, whoſe ſacred Fires melt down the hardeſt Hearts, whoſe holy Aids are ſufficient to help our Infirmities, and whoſe Fruits are Repentance, and Peace, and Joy: O do thou direct, aſſiſt and guide my
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:32171:36"/>ſoul, and keep me in all thy ways.</p>
                  <p>O thou that leadeſt the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant to the Truth, ſinners to Repentance and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and art the Comforter of the ſad and wounded ſoul: O do thou open my eyes to ſee the errors of my ways, and my heart to hate and forſake them, and let thy Grace and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts guide me in all my diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and ſupport me in all my trials.</p>
                  <p>O Bleſſed Spirit, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the dangers that encompaſs, and the temptations that beſet, and moſt eaſily prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me: O be thou my Guide, and never leave me nor
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:32171:37"/>forſake me; but from the deceit of my heart, from the wiles of Satan, and the ſad effects of ill Opinions, Melancholy and Deſpair, Good Lord, deliver me.</p>
                  <p>O good God, give me not up to my ſelf, and withdraw not thy Grace from me, but aſſiſt and accept my Prayers and my Repentance, and hear thy Son, that is making inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for me; let his Blood atone for me, and by his Stripes let my ſoul be healed.</p>
                  <p>O merciful Father, who wouldſt have me repent and live, and by whoſe Grace and Aid I have here proſtrated my ſelf before thee, to confeſs and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:32171:37"/>bewail my ſins, and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to forſake them: O do thou, who knoweſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of my Heart, the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my beſt Reſolutions, and the power and prevalence of my corrupt Nature, let thy Grace be ſufficient for me, and the helps of thy Spirit make my ſorrow ſincere, my reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſtedfaſt, and ſo change and conſecrate my Affections, that they may never more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guide me.</p>
                  <p>O thou that art the Maker and Lover of Souls, Hear my Prayer, Forgive my Sins, Accept my Sorrows, Streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my Reſolutions, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm my Vows, and grant me
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:32171:38"/>Repentance to Life Eternal, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:32171:38"/>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>5. A Prayer for Grace.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt merciful Father, who knoweſt my inability to do any thing that is good without thee, and with what ſubtilty and diligence the Devil lies in wait to deceive and ruine my Soul: O good God, let thy ſtrength appear in my weakneſs, and diſcover and diſappoint the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Deſtroyer, and deliver me from the corrupt inclinations of my own nature. Thou haſt promiſed to give the aſſiſtance of thy Holy Spirit to thoſe that ask it, let that bleſſed Spirit direct and guide to, and keep me in all thy ways, let it never leave me, nor forſake me, nor be withdrawn from me, but keep me in thy fear, and in thy ways, till it bring me to thy preſence and thy glory, through the merits of Jeſus Chriſt, my bleſſed Saviour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:32171:39"/>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="part">
                  <head>6. A Prayer for Faith.</head>
                  <p>O Almighty God, who art the Author and Giver of every good thing; Purge out of my heart all Diſtruſt and Infidelity, and every mean and unworthy thought of thy ſelf: Lord, help my unbelief, and beget, continue, and confirm in my Soul ſuch a lively, active, and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Faith, as may ſhew it ſelf in Piety and good Works, and be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to my Salvation, among thoſe who <hi>have not ſeen, and yet believe;</hi> that He who is the Author, Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Finiſher of our Faith, and has promiſed Life to thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in and through his Name, may at laſt ſay unto me, <hi>Come, thou good and faithful ſervant, enter into the joys of my reſt;</hi> which I humbly beg for Chriſt Jeſus his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:32171:39"/>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="part">
                  <head>7. A Prayer for Holineſs.</head>
                  <p>O Almighty God, who ſeeſt the frailties of my Nature, and knoweſt how great the difficulties, how numerous the temptations are that beſet me, and how hard it is for Man that is born of a Woman to be clean before thee, and yet haſt declared, <hi>That without Holineſs no man ſhall ſee thy face in glory:</hi> O Lord, with an eye of pity look down upon me, let thy Grace ſupply the defects of my Nature, and that mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Providence that watches over us for our good, keep back or deliver me from every temptation; and that Goodneſs that is able to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate my affections, be always ready to direct and guide me in all my deſigns and ways, that thy Holineſs may be my aim, and thy Glory my deſire, and the aſſiſtances of thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit carry my affections to things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:32171:40"/>and ſo purifie me from all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit, that I may be holy as Thou art holy, that my Converſation may be in Heaven, and a holy and unblama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Life fit me for that ſtate of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs that is the reward of the Saints above. Hear and anſwer me, O Lord for Chriſt Jeſus ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="part">
                  <head>8. A Prayer for due preparation for Death and Judgment.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God, whoſe hands have made and faſhioned us out of the duſt, and haſt in thy Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice pronounced, <hi>That to duſt we muſt return again,</hi> and <hi>appointed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all men once to die, and after that to Judgment;</hi> and by my own frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the reproaches of my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, haſt given me ſuch certain preſages of my Death, and the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I am to give, that I ſhall be inexcuſable if I be found unprovided
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:32171:40"/>for them. O good God, let the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices thou haſt given me keep me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways mindful of what I am, and what I muſt be; and the thoughts of Death and Judgment ſo conduct the whole courſe of my life, that when it is thy pleaſure to call me, I may be fit to die, and give up my Account with joy, and a juſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his favour and love, who is my Saviour and my Judge, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:32171:41"/>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="part">
                  <head>9. The Penitent's Prayer of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation, or devoting himſelf to God.</head>
                  <p>O Bleſſed Father, by whoſe Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er all things were made, and for whoſe ſervice and pleaſure they were created, and in reſignation to whoſe holy will all our felicity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, in mercy look down upon a Prodigal thy Grace and Goodneſs has brought to a ſenſe of his Duty: I have ſinned againſt Heaven and before thee, and am unworthy to be called thy Child; but it is thy will I ſhould return, and thou art pleaſed to receive me as a ſervant. O bleſſed Father, I reſign my ſelf to thy ſervice, to be diſpoſed as thou ſeeſt fitteſt for me: Thine ſhall be my will; I will eſteem that wiſe and holy, thou commandeſt; true, that thy word promiſes or affirms; juſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:32171:41"/>and reaſonable, thou appointeſt; and will believe it my greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to follow where thou art plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call me. And here, O Lord, I offer and preſent unto thee my Soul and Body, to be a holy and a reaſonable Sacrifice to thee. What thy Grace has made thine, let thy Goodneſs accept and preſerve, and thy Spirit ſeal to the day of Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:32171:42"/>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="part">
                  <head>10. A Prayer for the Church.</head>
                  <p>O Bleſſed Father, by whoſe Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and good Providence thy Truth has been planted and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in theſe Nations; In mercy look down upon that Church thy own right hand has planted therein; make us ſo ſenſible of the advantages of a holy and uncorrupt Faith, of the truly pious and decent Worſhip, and the Bleſſings of uncorrupted and undiſguiſed Truth we enjoy in her Communion; that laying aſide our Heats and Prejudices, we may all ſtudy the Peace and Honour of our Holy Mother, and our unhappy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions give no occaſion to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Reformation to attempt or hope our Ruine. More eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I beſeech thee to give me Grace in my place and calling to live an uſeful Member of this thy Church, till thou ſhalt call me to thy Church
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:32171:42"/>in Glory. All this I beg for his ſake who died for, and is the Head of the Church, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="part">
                  <head>11. A Prayer for theſe Kingdoms.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God, by whoſe Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we are preſerved from Confuſion and Ruine; Forgive our fins, and continue thy Mercies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, and by thy Wiſdom and Bleſſing preſerve and ſecure the Peace and Honour of theſe Nations; Make the Government thou haſt eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great Inſtrument of promoting thy Honour, eſtabliſhing thy Goſpel, and ſecuring the Peace, the Welfare, and Proſperity of the People of theſe Kingdoms, and make them ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Bleſſings they enjoy there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that we may all ſtudy to be qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and live in Peace, and Love, and Piety, till thou think fit to receive us to thy eternal Kingdom, thorough Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:32171:43"/>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="part">
                  <head>12. A Prayer for the People of theſe Kingdoms.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God, who ſeeſt what ill uſe we have made of thy great Mercies toward us; how we have abuſed thy Grace and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; how we are fallen from that Innocence and Vertue, from that Plaineſs and Integrity, that were once the Honour of theſe Nations; and how far that unhappy Spirit of Scoffing, Irreligion and Profaneneſs have prevailed amongſt us: O Lord, if it be thy will, put a ſtop to our Profaneneſs, and let our Wickedneſs come to an end; revive a Spirit of Holineſs and Sincerity, of Juſtice and Temperance, of Charity and Peace, and make us that happy People <hi>who have the Lord for our God,</hi> for Chriſt Jeſus his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:32171:43"/>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Occaſional Prayers to be added.</head>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>On <hi>Good-Friday.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Holy Father, who haſt ranſack'd thy own boſom for arguments of pity, and in thy compaſſion taken meaſure by thy infinite and unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Goodneſs, and for thy Mercies ſake given thy Son to be a Ranſom and a Peace-offering for thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: In Him in whom thou art well pleaſed, look down upon me; let his Sacrifice of himſelf atone for my ſins, his Blood make my peace, and by his Stripes let my Soul be healed, O God my God. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:32171:44"/>
                     <head>Another Prayer for <hi>Good-Friday.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Moſt Holy and Ever-bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who waſt pleaſed to die for ſinners, Have pity and compaſſion upon me, a miſerable ſinner: and that the imitation of thy Life and Sufferings may fit me for the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and Bleſſings thereof, let thy Grace and Goodneſs give a due in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to thy Example; let thy exemplary Patience and holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation teach me to reſign my ſelf and my will to the Hand and the Will of God in all his diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; thy Charity to forgive; thy Meekneſs to humble every aſpiring thought, and preſerve a Spirit calm and eaſie amidſt all the Injuries and Provocations that befal me; let the Power of thy Death overcome all my propenſities to ſin, and thy
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:32171:44"/>Sufferings atone for it: and ſince thou liveſt for ever to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for ſinners, and haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſave to the uttermoſt all ſuch as come unto thee, Lord, hear my Prayers, forgive my Sins, and ſave me in the day of Wrath, O thou Lamb of God that takeſt away the ſins of the world. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>For <hi>Aſh-Wednesday,</hi> or any other time of <hi>Lent.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Almighty God, who art always ready to give thy aſſiſtance to every good thought, every honeſt intention, and ſincere endeavour to conſecrate our ſelves to thy ſervice, yet haſt taught us to hope for the Aids of thy Grace in the uſe of Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Prayer, Mortification and Self-denial, and all other uſeful ways of ſubduing the Luſts of the fleſh: Give, O Lord, thy Bleſſings and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:32171:45"/>to all that humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before thee; accept their Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, hear their Prayers, and forgive their Sins. Bleſs me, O my Father, let thy Spirit help my Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and ſo aſſiſt me, that my fleſh being ſo ſubdued to the Spirit, my Faſting may be conſecrated to thee, who ſeeſt in ſecret, and thou mayeſt reward me openly, among thoſe who by keeping themſelves from the defilements of the fleſh, ſhall be fitted to follow the Lamb for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. All this I beg for his ſake who faſted for ours, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:32171:45"/>
                     <head>For the <hi>Thirtieth of <hi>January.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Almighty God, who in thy Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice didſt ſuffer theſe Nations to fall into Anarchy and Confuſion, and involve themſelves in the guilt of innocent Blood, the Blood of thine Anointed: Look in mercy upon us, and forgive our ſins, eſpecially That of <hi>This Day;</hi> let it never be laid to our charge, and do thou ſpare us when thou makeſt inquiſition for Blood, and make us ſo ſenſible of our great provocations, that we may all turn from the evil of our ways, and our iniquities may not be our ruine. O do thou, who art the God of Peace, and Love, and Order, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire us all with a Spirit of Holineſs and Charity, of Meekneſs and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and make us the People who have the Lord for our God, for Chriſt Jeſus ſake, our Saviour and Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:32171:46"/>
                     <head>For the <hi>Second of <hi>September,</hi>
                        </hi> being the <hi>Fire of <hi>London.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Almighty God, whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are terrible, and whoſe Mercies are infinite, who haſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thy diſpleaſure at our ſins, in permitting the deſtroying Angel to kill thouſands in our ſtreets, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſurfeiting the Grave with our Dead; and when this would not reclaim us, in laying waſte our Dwellings, and giving us ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a remembrance of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> in our puniſhment by fire. O Lord, make us all ſenſible of our provocations that have drawn down thy anger, and let thy Judgments drive, or thy Goodneſs lead us all to Repentance: Awake us from our Security, and drive out that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Spirit of Profaneneſs and Luxury, that has ſo long prevailed, and raiſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:32171:46"/>up amongſt us a Spirit of Holineſs and Wiſdom, of Temperance and Charity, and teach us all to live in thy fear and in thy favour. O Lord, forgive whatever I have contributed to the crying ſins of the Nation, and let my iniquity never draw thy anger upon thy People, but make me an Inſtrument of doing thee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:32171:47"/>
                     <head>For any Day of publick <hi>Faſting.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Almighty God, who haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to forgive the ſins and hear the Prayers of all ſuch as turn to thee by Repentance; In mercy look down on thy People, humbling themſelves before thee in Faſting and Prayer. O Lord, make us all ſenſible of our great provocations, and how juſt it would be in thee to give us up into the hands of thoſe men whoſe mercies are cruel, and pour out thy indignations upon us: But with thee, O Lord, there is mercy, that thou maiſt be feared; O do thou ſpare us, though we deſerve puniſhment, and in thy wrath think upon mercy; Give us not over unto confuſion, nor let our Enemies ſay, We have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed; but by a general Repentance and Reformation fit us for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and then be good unto us, as thou uſeſt to be to thoſe that love
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:32171:47"/>thy Name. Forgive, eſpecially, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I have contributed to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Guilts, or done to hinder thy Bleſſings, whether to Church or State; and give me ſuch a ſenſe thereof, that my preſent Repentance and future practice may be exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, and the courſe of my life fit me for ever to live with thee in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer before Receiving the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MOſt gracious Lord our God, who wouldeſt not have the Prodigal loſt, and haſt no pleaſure in the death of him that dies, but wouldſt have men come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of themſelves, thy Mercy, and thy Truth, that they may be ſaved; O holy Father, receive a relenting Prodigal to thy Arms, a Sinner to thy Mercy; and let thy Goodneſs
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:32171:48"/>ſo cover the errors of my paſt life, my preſent ſorrows for them, and my reſolutions of a better obedience, that I may be accepted at thy Table, that I may be admitted to all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of thy Son's Death and Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and his Blood may ſeal my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and the aſſiſtance of thy Grace direct and enable me ſo to live for the time to come, that I may at laſt be received, with all true Penitents, to thy Mercy, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>In the time of <hi>Sickneſs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>O Merciful Lord, who uſeſt thy rod in anger as well as love, and expecteſt that we ſhould be bettered by every correction: With the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions of a Father look upon me, teach me to call my ways to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and find out the accurſed thing that has brought this affliction upon me; and make me ſo ſenſible
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:32171:48"/>of my manifold provocations, and ſo ſincerely to lament, and abhor, and forſake them, that this correction may appear the effect of thy love and pity, and by a ſerious and hearty Repentance, a lively Faith, and a juſt affiance in thy Mercy, fit me for <hi>the Night, in which none can work;</hi> that if thou thinkeſt fit to ſpare me, I may live an example of one bettered by thy Judgment; or elſe reap the benefits of thy fatherly correction in an entire ſubmiſſion to thy will here, and being received to thy Glory hereafter. All for Chriſt Jeſus his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:32171:49"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>His method of arming himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the temptations of the world, and ſtrengthening his reſolutions, by reflecting, 1. On Death, and the dangers of delaying Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. 2. The Judgment to come. 3. Love of God. 4. Prayer for Love of God. 5. General Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THus the Penitent having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged his Soul into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of a God forgiving Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, Tranſgreſſion, and Sin, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed with the hopes of pardon; and a proſpect of that Goodneſs he is henceforward to adore and imitate, and the peace and joy of an eaſie conſcience, raiſe ſo amiable an Idea of Vertue and Holineſs, that he fears
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:32171:49"/>nothing more than that the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhould be loſt, that his reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould languiſh: 'Tis therefore his next care, to fix a ſenſe of his paſt tranſgreſſions, and perpetuate the ſatisfactions of the change he has made, and carry back with him to his ſtation in this world, ſuch a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the Honour and Service of God, as may animate the whole courſe of his converſation; and, leſt the objects of ſenſe, or his too partial regard to his worſe part, leſſen his concern for that better Subject of his love and care, the bleſſed Image of his great Creator, he endeavours to arm himſelf with ſuch Reflections as theſe:</p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>1. His Reflections on Mortality and Death, and the danger of a late Repentance.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. WHilſt I careleſly tread upon the aſhes of my Anceſtors, and the pleaſures of ſenſe cloud the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:32171:50"/>notices my Creator has given me of Mortality, my Senſes do the buſineſs of my Reaſon; for my Body gives me ſuch certain notices of its own mortal ſtate, that I am as certain I muſt die, as I can be that I am not a Stock or a Stone, that I have the ſenſe of feeling, or am uneaſie when my blood is in a flame, or when I am crying out of the pains of the Gout or Stone: But whether the thread of my life ſhall regularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, or make but one ſhort flame, is a ſecret I cannot penetrate; the time and manner of my Death are equally unknown to me; I have no better aſſurance <hi>in what manner</hi> I muſt leave the world, than <hi>when</hi> I muſt do it; my Reaſon and my Senſes may go before me, and Death may ſeize me when I am able neither to ſpeak nor think, much leſs reflect or beg pardon; and there is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in the Grave; but as I leave this world, Judgment will overtake
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:32171:50"/>me in the other: or it may ſeize me in the very act of ſin, when my ſoul is poured out upon my Luſts, and all my faculties and all my affections are engaged in my Folly; and ſhould I be thus ſurprized, with what confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and aſtoniſhment ſhould I appear before Him that hates my ſin, and all in vain did ſo much to prevent my ruine? and what can I hope for, when my life ſhall appear but one long ſcene of contempt and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his Law, and the very laſt act of it a defiance of the remedy God had tendred to me? But if Death make a gentle and eaſie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and the mercy of God deliver me from the numberleſs contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that may prevent all poſſibility of a late Repentance; what aſſurance can I have, that what till then had been my choice, will not then become my doom? or that God will not give me up to a penal hardineſs? But if God permit me to be ſenſible of my
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:32171:51"/>danger, yet with what face can I hope for, or ask the aſſiſtance of his Grace, that I not only not deſired, but refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and reſiſted, till I am become un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of uſing it to his Honour? But if God give me grace to be ſenſible of my paſt ſins, yet this is at the moſt but one part of Repentance, and ſuch as can afford me little comfort, when my circumſtances put me out of a poſſibility of reducing my ſorrow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to practice; for tho's God, who knows the heart, and does ſometimes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the will for the deed, when that will is ſincere, yet He only is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judge of that ſincerity, and not the Chriſtian, unleſs he have time to try it by his practice. So that the beſt aſſurance the late Penitent can have of the truth of his ſorrow, is at the moſt but the aſſurance he has of the ſincerity of his heart, which is deceitful above all things. What mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is it then to venture Eternity on that which is but the ſhadow of a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:32171:51"/>well-grounded hope, a ſhadow that may flie away in a moment, a ſhadow that the Harbingers of Death ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently remove from us, that if God had made a promiſe to accept the ſorrows of dying perſons to all the ends of Repentance, the methods by which Death makes its approach would very often render it ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual, by putting it out of the power of dying perſons ſo much as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what they had done.</p>
                  <p>Thus the Chriſtian views the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice, and beholds the dangers of thoſe delays corrupted Nature, or the flatteries of the world would lead him to; and concludes it as neceſſary to be always provided for it, as it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain he is to die, and looks upon it as his moſt important care, not to loſe the happy minute on which an eternity of Bliſs or Miſery depends: but the danger of a ſad Eternity keeps him always upon his guard; and the conſideration, that the juſtice
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:32171:52"/>of God, or the frailties of his Nature, may in a minute raviſh from his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the opportunity to make his peace, poſſeſſes him with a ſteddy reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to live over his ſorrows, his vows and promiſes, and endeavour that the practice or fruits of true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, amendment, and doing better, may fit him for the change God and Nature have made inevitable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>2. His Reflections on Judgment.</head>
                  <p n="2">2 COuld I hide my ſins in the duſt, would the ſame kind Fate that cloſes up mine eyes, hide me to eternal Ages, or the Grave ſpread night over all my actions; could I lie forgotten there, and ſhare the portion of the Worm that muſt then be my brother; or could that corruption and rottenneſs that are to be my ſiſter and my mother, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title me to an everlaſting oblivion and neglect, a ſhort-liv'd ſhame, and the uneaſineſs and diſhonour of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:32171:52"/>doing an unworthy action, might poſſibly be too little to reſtrain my unruly paſſions.</p>
                  <p>But whilſt my Luſt thus fondly entertains me, my Reaſon breaks through the ſcene of Folly, the regret every ſin leaves behind it, the ſecret pleaſures of well-doing, the ſeeming inequality in the diſpenſations of Providence, the indelible notices of the Divine Being and Juſtice, give me ſuch certain preſages of a future Account, that amidſt the charms of ſin, I find ſomething like St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s ſound, <hi>To Judgment;</hi> ſomething that ſpreads a ſecret pleaſure or regret through my Soul, for actions un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to all the world; and leaves ſuch impreſſions upon me, that 'tis as eaſie to put off my Nature, and ceaſe to be whilſt I am, as to deliver my Soul from the apprehenſions of a future Judgment.</p>
                  <p>But had Nature been ſilent, He that made and governs the world has
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:32171:53"/>given us a proſpect of futurity, and ſhewed us how he will rectifie the ſeeming inequalities that appear in the conduct of human affairs, and with an impartial hand deal Reward or Puniſhment to all his Subjects. But can nothing be hid from the diſcerning Eye? muſt my youthful follies, muſt the elaborate ſins I have ſpun ſo fine as to carry the face of Virtue to the world, paſs the cenſure of juſt Omniſcience? muſt my var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed Luſts, my gilded Paſſions, and my painted Sins, be ſtripped na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and thus appear to the Judge of Secrets? muſt my avowed Impieties and cuſtomary Sins, my known and unobſerved Omiſſions, every tumor in my Paſſions, every indecency in my Words, every fooliſh Thought, be brought into Account? and will God enter into Judgment for them? muſt the follies I did not dare to truſt to a mortal eye, nay ſcare to the cenſure of my own conſcience,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:32171:53"/>be proclaimed to Men and Angels? muſt I anſwer to God for every Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy I have abuſed, every opportunity of Repentance I have loſt; for every inſtance of that patience and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that have been vouchſafed to me in vain? Good God! what muſt a ſinner do! If thou wilt be extreme to mark all I have done amiſs, I cannot anſwer thee one for a thouſand; and how then ſhall I ſtand in judgment! and yet I cannot flie from, nor avoid or illude it: <hi>If I climb up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, thou art there; if I go down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell, thou art there alſo.</hi> Thy Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſence fruſtrates all my hopes of flying on the wings of the morning, and thy Power the kindneſs of the Mountains, ſhould they fall upon me. From thy preſence then I cannot flee from thy Spirit I cannot hide me, and, which is more dreadful, not the leaſt of all my fins.</p>
                  <p>But whilſt this dreadful proſpect fills the ſoul of the Penitent with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:32171:54"/>and horror, the comforts of the bleſſed Spirit (that ever watch the motions of the wounded ſoul) break in upon him, and carry his thought to new reflections on the compaſſions of his Judge; He remembers that he who muſt come to call him to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, is the ſame bleſſed Perſon that died to ſave him, and in charity to him came from Heaven, to ſhew him how to flie from the wrath to come, and has offered him his hand to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct him to his arms. Thus his fears reſolve into a nobler paſſion, and his confuſion breaks up in reſolutions to accept the tenders of his Lord, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all his future actions by a regard to this great Account; and this one thought, <hi>That his Lord may come in a day or an hour that he looks not for him, and appoint him his portion with unbelievers,</hi> is guard to all the reſt; the flatteries with which his Luſt or Vanity uſed to poſſeſs his fancy, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear empty Dreams; the charms of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:32171:54"/>this Luſt, and that temptation that once reigned with an uncontrouled power, ſhrink and wither at the thoughts of Judgment.</p>
                  <p>Thus the Penitent impales &amp; guards his reſolution, his vows and prayers; and under this conſideration, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns of his ſorrow and penitence, appear always wiſe and reaſonable.</p>
                  <p>But leſt this Picture of Repentance ſhould ſeem all ſhadow, and leave too dark and melancholy impreſſions on the Penitent, his next care is, To form in his ſoul ſuch images of the Eternal Goodneſs, that a principle of Love may conduct his fears and ſorrows, and ſuch a value and eſteem of that adorable pattern he is to imitate, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate a holy reverence and awe, that love that may ſuperſede every thing that is uneaſie in his fears, and inſpire a ſecret pleaſure and delight in all the methods of Virtue and Religion. For this end, he entertains himſelf with the contemplation of that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:32171:55"/>Love and Mercy to ſinners that preſent themſelves in the Paſſion of his Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>His Reflections on the Death and Sufferings of Chriſt, and the Love of God viſible therein.</head>
                  <p>THat he who made Man after his own likeneſs, and deſigned him a partaker in the felicities him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf enjoys, ſhould love his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and with pity and concern ſee it defaced and loſt, is ſo natural a thought, that the ſame notices which diſcover his Being, preſent it to us as the moſt adorable Object; in Mercy boundleſs, in Love and Goodneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite: Thus it ſeems poſſible to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the Mercies of Creation and Providence; but the whole me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Man's Redemption is ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious and amazing, that 'tis ſome pain to form any <hi>Idea</hi> of it, but impoſſible to think, much more to ſpeak of it, or entertain it, with
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:32171:55"/>the reſentment it deſerves. That he who knows that we are but duſt ſhould pity and forgive is eaſie to conceive; but that he ſhould give a Beloved in exchange for a Rebellious Son, part with the expreſs Image of his Perſon to reſtore that Man had abuſed, defaced and loſt; that he ſhould give a Son from his Boſom to bring an Enemy thither, and let him dye in whom he was well pleaſed, to fit them to live, who had made Death their Choice, and Deſtruction their wiſh, is a heighth of Love beyond the boldeſt Wiſhes and moſt aſpiring Hopes; that he who was poſſeſs'd of immenſe Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city before the World began, ſhould come down from Heaven to take that Nature which had deſerved his Anger; that he who was over all God Bleſſed for ever, ſhould be led like a Lamb to the ſlaughter, for his ſake who deſerved to have been an Eternal Sacrifice to Juſtice; that he
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:32171:56"/>alone ſhould tread the Wine-preſs of his Father's Wrath, for him who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had merited the dregs of the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cup; that he ſhould be wounded for the Sins that ought to pierce our own Souls, and bruiſed for the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions that might have ſunk us down in a deluge of Miſery, are ſuch inſtances of an amazing pity and love, that his Soul muſt be colder than the Earth, and his Heart harder than the Rocks, that can reſiſt them; but he muſt be a Monſter, ſomething that can neither love nor think, that can deſpite and contemn it. After all that God has thus done to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my Love, ſhall the flame that ought to melt only harden me? And the Blood ſhed upon the Croſs ſerve only to write my Name among thoſe that weep and howl for ever? Shall ſuch Miracles of Charity, ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing Goodneſs be loſt upon me?</p>
                  <p>No! No! I muſt not, I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt a being cloathed with every Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:32171:56"/>and Perfection, infinitely good in himſelf, and unſpeakable good to me; that is pleaſed with my Happineſs and delighted in my Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; deſerves the nobleſt Paſſion, and juſtly challenges all the Powers and Faculties of my Soul; to love is the leaſt return I can make, the ſmalleſt acknowledgement that is due to him, that gave his Son for us.</p>
                  <p>This conſideration, as it preſents the Penitent with an amazing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Charity and Juſtice; ſo it raiſes a Holy Emulation betwixt his Love and Fear; he loves that Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that pitied the Sinner, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veres the Juſtice that puniſhed his Sin; he adores the Charity that gave, but dreads the Juſtice that ſpared not his Son; his Love inſpires his fears, and a holy awe conducts his Love; he can eaſily reſolve not to offend the Being he cannot but Love, and can heartily lament it whenever he breaks his reſolution, and is always
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:32171:57"/>uneaſie till he has begged Pardon and be reconciled again.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <head>His Prayer for the Love of God.</head>
                  <p>ALmighty God, whoſe infinite Perfections and Excellency, whoſe immenſe Goodneſs and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence juſtly render thee the moſt amiable and adorable Being, worthy of all Love and Obedience, and in reſpect of whom every thing is but vain and contemptible, pour into my Heart ſuch Love towards thee, and imprint upon my Soul ſuch an <hi>Idea</hi> of thy Excellency and Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I may love thee with all my Mind, with all my Heart, and with all my Strength, and conſecrate all the Powers and Faculties of my Soul to thy Love and Service, that I may prefer thy favour above all things of this World, and a Love of thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire a cheerfulneſs into every Duty, and ſhed an influence upon every thing I ought to door ſuffer for thee;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:32171:57"/>and ſo poſſeſs my Soul that every thing may appear vain and empty that would withdraw me from thy Servce, and every thing eaſie and acceptable that thy Service requires from me, that I may ſo love, adore thee, and do thy will on Earth, that I may be fit to joyn with thoſe, whoſe Reward and Duty it is eternally to Love and ſerve thee in Heaven, for Chriſt Jeſus his ſake, who is the Son of thy Love. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>His Litany or ſhort Prayers.</head>
                  <p>O God the Father, God the Son, God the Holy Ghoſt, hide not thy ſelf from my Petitions, but hear my Prayers, and have Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on me.</p>
                  <p>O thou Creator and Preſerver of Man, by whoſe Power I was made, by whoſe Bounty I have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, by whoſe Grace and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance I hope to live to thee, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:32171:58"/>by whoſe Mercy and Goodneſs I hope to live eternally with thee, have Mercy upon me, and hear my Prayers.</p>
                  <p>O Bleſſed God, whom to know is Life, and to ſerve is perfect Freedom, whoſe ways are ways of Peace, and to do whoſe will is our Duty and Reward; O do thou teach me to know and love thee as I ought to do, and keep and guide me in all thy ways.</p>
                  <p>O thou that knoweſt what Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Temptations encompaſs me, how ſoon my beſt Reſolutions are broken, my beſt Purpoſes overcome, my moſt Solemn Promiſes and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate Vows rendred ineffectual, let thy Goodneſs be preſent in every Danger and Temptation, and thy Grace be always ſufficient for me.</p>
                  <p>From the ſnares of the World, the corruption of my Nature, the Arts and Deſigns of the Deſtroyer, from the miſchief of evil Council, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:32171:58"/>of bad Example, a great Danger, and an invincible Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>From the Flatteries of the Great, and the Snares of Proſperity, from the hardſhip and temptations of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, from the Luxury a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs of Plenty, from Pride and Haughtineſs in good Circumſtances and Dejection and Diſcontent in had, Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>From peeviſhneſs and ſpiritual Pride, the miſchiefs of vain and fond Opinions, an uneafie Temper and unruly Tongue, from raſh words and the ſurprizes of luſt and folly, and uncharitable thoughts and cenſures, Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>From an hard Heart and an evil Conſcience, from wilful Ignorance and Error and Knowledge that puffs up; from reſiſting or diſcouraging Truth, and promoting Error for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ends; from appearing or doing good for bad purpoſes, promoting
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:32171:59"/>chief under pretence of Religion, the abuſe of thy Grace, and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of a late repentance, Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>O Bleſſed Lord, from whom e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very good thing comes, to whom every thing is poſſible, and who out of Stones canſt raiſe up Children unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> have Mercy upon me, and make me ſuch as thou wouldſt have me to be, good Lord, I beſeech thee.</p>
                  <p>O Lord, in whoſe Hand are the Hearts of Men, and who turneſt them where thou wilt, create a clean Heart and a new Spirit within me, and turn me, Good Lord, that I may be turned.</p>
                  <p>Thou knoweſt how imperfect my Sorrows are, how eaſily my Vows are broken, and my beſt reſolutions brought to nothing: O do thou that dwelleſt with the humble and ſcontrite Heart, make mine truly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch, make my Sorrows ſincere and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:32171:59"/>my Reſolutions ſteddy, and let it be ever my ſtuddy and delight to do thy will, O God, my God.</p>
                  <p>Let thy Word be my Rule, thy Grace my Guide and Aſſiſtance, thy Goodneſs my Pattern and Example, thy Promiſes my Encouragement, and thy Joys my everlaſting Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence and Reward.</p>
                  <p>O let my Words be ſuch as may miniſter Grace to the Hearers, my demeanour innocent, inoffenſive, humble and eaſie, my Affections governable, and my Life exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary.</p>
                  <p>Let every Mercy have its due effect upon me, every opportunity of repentance make me better, and if a temptation prove too hard for me, let me not ſleep with an unrepented Sin in my Boſom; but give me a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent Heart, a watchful and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Conſcience.</p>
                  <p>Let thy Goodneſs and Beneficence be my Pattern; and make me uſeful
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:32171:60"/>in the ſtation thou haſt placed me in; give me a Heart and give me Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ability to do good; and let ſuch a temper and diſpoſition of Soul, as delights in the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, recommend me to that Charity that is pleaſed with the Sacrifices of well doing.</p>
                  <p>O good God! to whom every thing is poſſible, ſanctifie my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature, and let thy gracious aids ſupply all my defects, and ſo help my Infirmities that I may live in thy Love and Fear, may die in thy Favour, and be prepared for the account I am to give, and be received with thy Faithful Servants to the joy of thy reſt.</p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:32171:60"/>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A concluding Prayer, recommending himſelf to God, imploring his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Favour, and Acceptance, and grace to live in his Fear and Love.</head>
                  <p>O Bleſſed Father, by whoſe Grace and Goodneſs I have been brought to ſome ſenſe of my ſins, and ſome imperfect endeavours to make my peace with thee by Repentance: In pity and compaſſion look down upon a poor ſinner thy Grace has brought into thy preſence; Proſper, O Lord, the work of thine own hand; Receive a Prodigal thy Mercy has brought back to thy Arms; For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give all thou haſt ſeen amiſs in my approaches to thee, and accept and perfect my deſires of being reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to thee, and living in thy Love and Favour, and give me ſuch aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of thy Grace, that for the time to come I may live in thy fear and favour, and by Peace and Charity, by Temperance and Integrity, by Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:32171:61"/>and Righteouſneſs, approve the ſincerity and truth of my ſorrow and repentance for my paſt tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. O Lord, into thy hands I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſelf; To thy keeping, O my God, I commit my Soul and my Body; Preſerve me from every ſin &amp; every danger, keep me always mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of my promiſes and reſolutions of Obedience, of Death and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of thy preſence, and the great Account I am to give; that ſo I may be always fitted and prepared to ſerve and glorifie thee, by a right uſe of thoſe Bleſſings thou haſt committed to my truſt, fitted to be received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thy faithful Servants into the Joys of thy Reſt. O Lord, hear and anſwer, pity and forgive me, and be good to me beyond what I can ask or think: And all for his ſake who died for ſinners; To whom with Thee and thy holy Spirit, be aſcribed all Adoration and Honour, all Praiſe and Thanks, both now and for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:32171:61"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>His behaviour after his retirement, or ſome ſhort Rules by which he endeavours to manifeſt the ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Repentance and Love of God. 1. In his diligence in his Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Juſtice in his Dealings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. Good of fices to all men. 3. Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, as a Subject. 4. Charity, as a Chriſtian. 5. Watchfulneſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all his Actions, and wiſe and ſober uſe of God's Bleſſings.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <p>THe devout Chriſtian having thus enquired into the ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his own ſoul, returns to his ſtation in the world, and chearfully ſets himſelf to do his Duty; in which each circumſtance has a particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard: He is induſtrious in his Calling,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:32171:62"/>and his juſtice in all his dealings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate his Cares and his Wealth to God. He knows that Godlineſs has the promiſe of this, as well as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, and aſſures himſelf of God's Bleſſing upon his Induſtry: But if God withhold his hand, or keep back his bounty, he believes the wiſe Diſpoſer of all things ſees it fitteſt for him, and quietly ſubmits; if God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper his Cares, he is humble, and thankful, and charitable, and God has the honour of his own Beneficence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <p>2. The frailties of his own Nature, and that immenſe Goodneſs that with an univerſal charity embraces Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, give him ſo lively a ſenſe of that regard he owes to human Nature, that he loves and prays for all Mankind, that he ſtudies to imitate the Divine Beneficence, in his endeavour to do good, and be uſeful in the world, and and by all the good offices of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Charity and Friendſhip, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Beneficence that is ever pleaſed with doing good.</p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:32171:62"/>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <p>3. That tendency to ſociety which he finds rivetted into his Natures, is cultivated and improved by a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to that Power and Providence by which the world is govern'd: He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves Government the Ordinance of God; and tho it always carries ſome marks of the frailties of men, yet this he looks upon as the infelicity eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the preſent ſtate of things, and thinks it a very unreaſonable peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to diſturb the publick Peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God thinks fit to govern us by men that have failings: but ſince this is the common ſtate of mankind, and till all Power be ſwallowed up in the Kingdom of the Father, there can be neither Governour nor Government without a fault, he believes he ought to contribute all he can to publick Peace, and ſtudy to be quiet.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <p>4. He bleſſes God for his unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Mercy in admitting him into the place of his Church; as a Member whereof, he believes there is a new tie
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:32171:63"/>laid upon him to preſerve the Peace and further the Welfare of all his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſtians, if they fall into Error, and violate either the Faith or the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of that bleſſed Society; he believes Chriſt is the Head and Judge to, and leaves the matter in his hand; and whilſt he adores the Goodneſs that has kept him in the ways of Truth and Peace, he preſerves a charity for thoſe who have departed from them: The holy ardour which inſpired the Devotions of his Cloſet, returns with him to his Calling, where he feels the rewards of it in a chearful acceſs to, and holy warmth in the publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; and the ſatisfaction he taſts in the care of his own Soul, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes a value and eſteem on thoſe that watch for it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <p>5. The peace and joys of a holy Conſcience, and the eaſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of being reconciled unto God, grow up into a reſolution to break through the tyranny of evil cuſtoms,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:32171:63"/>to fly every danger and temptation that have betray'd him to ſin, to watch every opportunity to ſerve God, or be uſeful to men, eſpecially not to bring a reproach on Religion, by being ſowr, or uneaſie, or fright men from a holy auſterity, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Accounts with God, by deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf the innocent joys of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; but on the contrary, his care is to do juſtice to the Honour of his Lord, by ſuch uſeful converſe, and decent and chearful uſe of God's Bleſſings, as may convince his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that the Chriſtian may be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate in plenty, humble in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, pious and devout in the higheſt ſtation or moſt publick Truſt, and hope for an inheritance in another world, without abandoning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent pleaſures and true joys of this, or doing any thing unworthy the greatneſs of his Birth, his Quality, or his Truſt, his Honour or Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, his good Breeding or good Temper</p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:32171:64"/>
                  <p>Thus reſolved, the Devout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian carries his Repentance into the light, and his Sorrows and Vows be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come viſible in Piety and Good Works: He lives over his Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a better Obedience, and his publick Actions beſpeak his Soul conſecrated to God, till ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy temptation break in upon him, ſome new Bleſſings call him back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; or the Joys of Peace, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with God, or his care of a future Account, call him afreſh to <hi>his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that ſees in ſecret.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 8. line 16. for <hi>removed</hi> read <hi>renewed.</hi> p. 26. l. 8. for <hi>ſins</hi> r. <hi>ſenſe.</hi> p. 69. l. 24. for <hi>hardineſs</hi> r. <hi>hardneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:64"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:66" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32171:66"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
